<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The varietie of memorable and worthy matters. By Walter Owsolde</title>
            <author>Owsolde, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849034</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 998:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The varietie of memorable and worthy matters. By Walter Owsolde</title>
                  <author>Owsolde, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I[ames] R[oberts] for Ieffery Charlton and are to be solde at his shoppe, at the great north doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Another state, STC 19002, omits printer's initials in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:1"/>
            <p>THE VARIETIE of Memorable and worthy matters.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Walter Owſolde.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by I. R. for <hi>Ieffery Charl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe, at the great North doore of Paules. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:2"/>
            <head>To the Right vvorſhipfull Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Romney,</hi> Knight and Alderman of the Cittie of London.</head>
            <p>RIght Worſhipfull, you may iustly thinke I am very bold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in reſpect a ſtranger vnto you, to offer vp theſe lines to your fauorable cenſure, yet the loue &amp; good affection which I owe to your worſhip for ſome ſufficient cauſes: may fully excuſe my raſhnes in that behalfe: and conſidering withall your gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſpoſition, hoping you will take in good part this meane gift, not reſpecting the value therof but the good will of the giuer, as did that woorthy King accepting with gentle hart a draught of water of a ſimple hind, ſo I expecting you will curteouſly vouchſafe the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing of theſe ſimple collexions, although there be nothing woorthy your reviewing contained therein, yet if you grant it but the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, you may finde ſome matter which may eyther delight you, by bringing into your remembrance ſuch memorable &amp; worthy things as haue hapned in former ages, or driue other drouſie thoughts out of your mind: which if it ſo come to paſſe, I ſhall haue the ful ſcope of my deſires, and be the more bolde an other time to offer to your view ſome thing of better worth. And ſo I leaue you to the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protection of Almighty God, whom I beſeech to bleſſe you with increaſe of worſhip, long life, and eternall happines.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to commaund Walter Owſold.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:3"/>
            <head>To the curtious Reader.</head>
            <p>WHen I conſider with my ſelfe gentle Reader, of the ſundry kinds of delights which men of diuers natures take pleaſure in: as ſom in reading ancient hiſtories, whereof there are many ſorts and kinds containing the amorous diſcourſes of young gallants, with the liues of their enamored Miſtreſſes, liuely diſciphering fooliſh dotage in old men &amp; ſtale widdowes, with the inconuenience of matching old age and wilfull youth together, and againe: ſome take pleaſure in reading Chronicles, declaring the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and worthy acts of valiant Captaines, and famous Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerners, with the changes and alterations of former times, which may much profite men of all ſorts. Therfore I thought good to publiſh this ſmall Treatiſe, taken and collected out of diuers ancient learned and well approoued authors, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary to be had in remembrance, which I hope the learned will take in good part, becauſe it ſaueth them a labour in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing ouer diuers volumes, to find the time and place where and when the matters heerein expreſſed, were begonne, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, continued, and ended; and as for the other ſort I hope they cannot miſlike it, treating of matters which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this booke they ſhould neuer haue knowne: and ſo I leaue it to your fauourable cenſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as you like this Booke, W. O.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:3"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE foure parts of the World. page, 1.</item>
               <item>The foure Monarchies. page, 1.</item>
               <item>The ſixe ages of the World. page, 2.</item>
               <item>The ſeauen wonders of the World. page, 4.</item>
               <item>The ſeauen Wiſemen of Greece. page, 5.</item>
               <item>The tenne Sibylls. page, 6.</item>
               <item>The twelue Apoſtles with theyr martyrdoms. page, 9.</item>
               <item>The ten perſecutions of Chriſtians vnder the Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours. page, 11.</item>
               <item>The eight times that Rome hath been taken. page, 11.</item>
               <item>The ſeauen Electors of the Emperours of Germanie. pa. 14.</item>
               <item>The three Crownes of the Emperour. page, 14.</item>
               <item>The twelue Peers or Pairs of Fraunce. page, 14.</item>
               <item>The eyght Parliaments of Fraunce. page, 15</item>
               <item>The ſeauen Saxon Kingdoms that England was once deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into. page, 17</item>
               <item>Fiue Orders of Chiualrie which continue at this day among Princes. page, 8</item>
               <item>The xiij. Cantons of Swiſſerland. pag. 22.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14164:4"/>
            <head>The foure parts of the world.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>SIA,</hi> ſo called of the Daughter of <hi>Ocean</hi> and <hi>Thetis,</hi> or as ſome ſay, of <hi>Aſia</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neé</hi> King of <hi>Lidia:</hi> is ſeperated from <hi>Europe</hi> by the riuer <hi>Tanais,</hi> nowe called <hi>Don,</hi> by the ſea called in time paſt <hi>Palus Meotides,</hi> now <hi>Mare de Zabache:</hi> and by <hi>Pontus Euxinus,</hi> now <hi>Mer maiour:</hi> and by part of the <hi>Mediterranian</hi> ſea: and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Africk</hi> by the riuer of <hi>Nile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe,</hi> that old Writers coniecture to be ſo called of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropa,</hi> daughter of <hi>Agenor</hi> King of <hi>Libia,</hi> is ſeperated from <hi>Aſia</hi> as is already ſhowne; and from <hi>Africk</hi> by the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Africke,</hi> which ſome ſay is ſo called of one <hi>Affer,</hi> of the line of <hi>Abraham,</hi> is ſeperated from <hi>Europe</hi> by the <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean ſea,</hi> and from <hi>Aſia</hi> by the riuer of <hi>Nile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>America,</hi> or <hi>West-India,</hi> ſo called of <hi>Americus Veſpuſius,</hi> but firſt found out by <hi>Christopher Columbus</hi> of <hi>Genua,</hi> the yere of our Lord 1492. It is in manner of an Iland, round about enuironed with the great <hi>Ocean ſea.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The foure Monarchies.</head>
            <p>THE firſt Monarchie was of the <hi>Aſſirians,</hi> founded by <hi>Ninus</hi> about the yere of the World 2220. augmented by the Queene <hi>Semiramis,</hi> and after it had endured the terme of 1300 yeeres, it was tranſlated by <hi>Arbactus</hi> vnto the <hi>Medes:</hi> and there hauing endured 350 yeeres, it was loſt by <hi>Astia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and conquered by <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Monarchie was of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> founded by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> the yeere of the World 3425, which after it had endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red 191 yeere, was loſt by <hi>Darius,</hi> and ſubdued by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14164:5"/>The third Monarchie was of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> founded by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the great, in the yeere of the world 3634, and before Chriſt 320 yeeres; after whoſe death it was deuided among the Prefects, which in his life time he had appointed in diuers countries: by which diuiſion <hi>Seleucus</hi> was King nf <hi>Syria, Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomeus</hi> of <hi>Egipt, Antigonus</hi> of <hi>Aſia, Caſſander</hi> of <hi>Macedonia</hi> &amp; <hi>Greece:</hi> all which cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries were after ſubdued by the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Monarchie or Empire was of the <hi>Romans,</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> the yere of the world 3914, after the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Rome</hi> 706 yeeres, and before Chriſt 47 yeeres. This Monarchie floriſhed about the ſpace of 470 yeeres, till that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the great, it was deuided by his two ſons into two Empires: <hi>Arcadius</hi> was Emperour of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> which Empire endured (though afterwards much dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the inuaſions of barbarous nations) vntill the yeere of our Lord 1453, and then was quite loſt by <hi>Constantine,</hi> and conquered by <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſecond king of <hi>Turks. Honorius</hi> was Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> which Empire ſhortly after, in the yeere of our Lord 475, &amp; about the ninth month of the raine of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus,</hi> was vtterly ruinated by <hi>Othacar</hi> king of <hi>Goths.</hi> And long after, the yere of our Lord 801 it was reſtored by <hi>Charles</hi> the great, and by him vnited to the crowne of <hi>France:</hi> and by his ſucceſſors tranſlated into <hi>Germanie,</hi> where it yet remaineth as a ſhadow onely, or repreſentation of the greatnes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of the ancient <hi>Romaine</hi> Empire.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſixe ages of the World.</head>
            <p>IN the deuiding of theſe ages, there is great contrarietie of opinions among Writers: for that ſome follow the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the 72 Interpreters, &amp; ſome follow the Hebrues, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon text of the Bible. The firſt age from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world till the vniuerſall flood, endured according to the Hebrues 1656 yeeres, which agreeth with the ſaying of Saint <hi>Hierom, Bede, Filo,</hi> and the common text of the Bible. The Seauentie two Interpreters, and <hi>Euſebius</hi> hold that it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured 2242 yeeres, and Saint <hi>Austine</hi> is of opinion, that it endured 2272. Of this age few or no things are recited wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14164:5"/>
of memory.</p>
            <p>The ſecond age from <hi>Noe</hi> his floud till the birth of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> endured according to the 72 Interpretours, <hi>Euſebeus,</hi> and the greateſt part of writers 942: and according to the Hebrewes but 292 yeares: Saint <hi>Austin</hi> counteth 172 yeares. In this age was builded <hi>The tower of confuſion:</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the <hi>Aſſirians</hi> beganne, and the great Citty of <hi>Niniue</hi> was builded, which contained in circuit three daies iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>The third age from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> endured by the agreement of all Authors 942 yeares. During this age was the peregrination of <hi>Abraham:</hi> the beginning of the <hi>Amazones, Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gommorre</hi> were deſtroyed: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was ſold to the <hi>Egiptians: Moiſes</hi> paſſed the red Sea: <hi>Iob</hi> the iuſt: <hi>Iaſon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the golden Fleece: the deſtruction of <hi>Troy:</hi> the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> beganne to raigne in <hi>Italie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth age from the beginning of the raigne of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> till the peregrination of the Iewes into <hi>Babilon,</hi> endured 485 yeares: during this age the Empire of <hi>Aſſirians</hi> was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the <hi>Medes,</hi> the <hi>Olimpiades</hi> of the <hi>Grecians</hi> beganne: <hi>Carthage</hi> was builded by <hi>Dido,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Romulus: Byzance</hi> was alſo builded: the diſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by <hi>Nabucodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor,</hi> and thereupon the captiuitie of the Iewes.</p>
            <p>The fift age from the tranſmigration of <hi>Babilon</hi> to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <hi>Christ,</hi> endured by the agreement of all, 589 yeares. During this age <hi>Cyrus</hi> beganne the Monarchie of the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> the 70 yeare of this age the Iewes returned to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: Conſuls began to rule in <hi>Rome: Zerxes</hi> inuaded <hi>Greece</hi> with an armie of 1000000 men: <hi>Plato, Aristotle,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mostenes</hi> flouriſhed with many other worthy Philoſophers: <hi>Alexander</hi> wonne the Monarchie of the world: the diſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Carthage</hi> by the <hi>Romaines: Caeſar</hi> vſurped the Empire of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sixt age beganne at the birth of our ſauiour <hi>Christ,</hi> which yet endureth, and ſhall endure to the end of the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14164:6"/>
            <head>The ſeauen wonders of the world.</head>
            <p>THe firſt, were the walls of <hi>Babilon,</hi> built by <hi>Semiramis,</hi> of ſtone ioyned together with a ſtrange kind of ſlimie and gluiſh morter, which groweth in the mines of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and eſpecially in the lake where ſtoode in time paſt <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Gommorre,</hi> now called <hi>Asfaltide.</hi> Theſe walls accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the towne, were built in quadrangle, and contained in circuit (as ſayeth <hi>Plinie</hi> in the 26 Chapter of his ſixt booke) 60 miles; ſo that euery ſquare was fifteene mile long; they were 200 foote high, and fiftie foote thicke: and to builde theſe walls were hired by <hi>Semiramis,</hi> out of diuers Countries for a long ſpace, 300000 men.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, was the <hi>Piller of the ſonne,</hi> offered by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles vnto <hi>Iupiter.</hi> This Piller ſtoode in the Ile of <hi>Rodes,</hi> and was made of yron, in the forme of a man of incredible great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; in ſo much that a man might ſcarce fadom the great finger thereof. After it had ſtood 56 yeares, it fell downe by reaſon of an earthquake, and ſo lay till the Iland was wonne by the Souldan of <hi>Egipt;</hi> who carried ſo much mettell away, as loaded 900 Camels.</p>
            <p>The third, were the <hi>Piramides</hi> of <hi>Egipt:</hi> among the which there is one eſpecially noted, about the Cittie of <hi>Memphis,</hi> now called the great <hi>Caire;</hi> this <hi>Piramis</hi> couered about 40 acres of land, at the foote or foundation thereof; it was all built of marble ſtone, and in the building thereof were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed continually, for the ſpace of 20 yeares, 3600000 men: and for the ſuſtenance of theſe workmen, was disburſt in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh and ſuch other rootes 1800 talents, which according to our reckening is the ſumme 1880000 crownes: this might ſeeme vncredible, were it not that it is affirmed by ſo many authors of authoritie.</p>
            <p>The fourth, was the <hi>Mauſol,</hi> of <hi>Mauſol</hi> King of <hi>Caria,</hi> and husband to <hi>Artemiſia</hi> ſo called: this woman for the great loue ſhe bare to her ſpouſe, burned his dead corps, and dranke the pouder thereof, thinking no Sepulcher ſo worthy thereof, as her owne body; and the reſt of the pouder ſhe buried in this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14164:6"/>
famous Tomb, the ſtone whereof was of an excellent kind of marble: it was 411 feete in circuit, and 25 cubits high, and was enuironed about with 36 Pillers of ſtone, wonderfully well carued.</p>
            <p>The fift, was the Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> builded by the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zones:</hi> it was 455 foote long, and 220 foote broad, and in it ſtood 127 marble Pillers, each of them being 70 foote high: the worke thereof was ſo wonderfull curious, that it was 220 yeares a making.</p>
            <p>The ſixt, was the image of <hi>Iupiter Olimpique,</hi> in <hi>Achaie;</hi> all of Porfire, an infinite number of little peeces ioyned together: this image beſide the excellencie of the worke, is eſpecially noted for the greatneſſe thereof, and was the more famous by reaſon of the gamigs, called <hi>Olimpiades,</hi> there kept.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth, was the Tower <hi>Faros,</hi> nigh vnto <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egipt,</hi> builded by <hi>Ptolomée Philadelphe</hi> King of <hi>Egipt,</hi> to direct the paſſengers which came to take hauen thereabouts, by burning of pitch, or other like things in the toppe: this Tower was of a meruailous height, and ſinguler workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the building whereof coſt according to our money 480000 crownes. Some authors put for the ſeauenth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the <hi>Gardens</hi> and <hi>Orchards</hi> vpon the walls of <hi>Babilon.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers put the <hi>Obeliſque</hi> of <hi>Semiramis,</hi> which differreth in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>Piramis,</hi> ſauing that it is all of one ſtone: the <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſque, Semiramis</hi> cauſed to be wraught, and taken out of the mountaines of <hi>Armenia:</hi> it was a hundreth and fifty foote high, and euery ſquare was foure and twenty foote braod at the bottome; ſo that it contained in circuit 96 foote.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſeauen wiſe men of Greece.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Blas</hi> borne in the hauen Towne of <hi>Prieme,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Ionia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solon</hi> borne in the Iland of <hi>Salamine. Chilo</hi> borne in <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia. Cleobulus</hi> borne at <hi>Lind</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Rhodes. Pittacus</hi> borne at <hi>Mycilene</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Lesbos. Thales</hi> borne at <hi>Mileto</hi> in <hi>Greece. Periander</hi> King of <hi>Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14164:7"/>
            <head>The tenne Sibylles.</head>
            <p>THe firſt was of <hi>Perſia,</hi> called <hi>Samberta:</hi> which among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophecies ſayd. The womb of the Virgine ſhall be the ſaluation of Gentiles.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was of <hi>Libia,</hi> one of her Prophecies were. The day ſhall come that men ſhall ſee the King of all liuing things, and a Virgine Lady of the world ſhall hold him in her lap.</p>
            <p>The third was <hi>Themis,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Delphica,</hi> becauſe ſhee was borne and prophecied, at <hi>Delphos.</hi> A Prophet ſhall bee borne of a Virgine.</p>
            <p>The fourth was <hi>Cuméa,</hi> borne at <hi>Cimerie</hi> a Cittie of <hi>Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> in <hi>Italia:</hi> who prophecied, that God ſhould be borne of a Virgine, and conuerſe among ſinners.</p>
            <p>The fift was the famous <hi>Erithraea,</hi> borne at <hi>Babilon:</hi> who eſpecially prophecied a great part of our Chriſtian religion, in certaine verſes recited by <hi>Euſebeus;</hi> the firſt letters of euerie which verſes being put together, make theſe words, <hi>Ieſus, Christ, Son of God, Sauiour.</hi> Theſe verſes are tranſlated into Latine by Saint <hi>Austine</hi> Lib. 18, and 23, <hi>de ciuitate dei:</hi> the ſubſtance whereof followeth. The earth ſhall ſweate ſigne of iudgement: from heauen ſhall come a King which ſhall raigne for euer, that is to ſay, in humaine fleſh, to the end that by his preſence he iudge the world, ſo the vnfaithfull aſwell as the faithfull ſhall ſee God with their eies aloft among his Saints; and in the end of the world, the ſoules of men with their bodies ſhall appeare; whom hee ſhall iudge when the roundneſſe of the earth, vntilled ſhall be full of clods of earth and graſſe, men ſhall caſt away their idols, and all their preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iewels, the world ſhall be conſumed with fire, hee ſhall pierce the inferiour parts, and breake the gates of darke hell: then to the fleſh of Saints ſhall be giuen free and cleere light, and the euill ſhall be burned with eternall fire, all ſecrets ſhall be opened, and euery one ſhall knowe the ſecret of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and God ſhall diſcouer the conſciences and harts of all men: then ſhall there be lamentation and gnaſhing of teeth, the Sunne and Starres ſhall looſe their light, the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14164:7"/>
ſhall be deſſolued, &amp; the Moone ſhall be darkened, the mountaines ſhall be throwne downe, and the valeis ſhall bee made equall with them, there ſhall bee nothing in the world higher or lower then another, mountaines and valleis ſhall be made plaine, all things ſhall ceaſe; the earth ſhall be dryed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to pouder and duſt, the fountaines and riuers shall be burned likewiſe, then shall a trumpet ſound from heauen in wofull &amp; horrible manner, and the opening of the earth shall diſcouer confuſed and darke hell, with the torments and paines of the miſerable condemned, and heere before the iudge shall come euery King: a riuer of fire &amp; brimſtone shal fall from heauen. Diuers other things were prophecied by this <hi>Sibylle:</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were obſcure, and therefore not to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Gentiles before they came to paſſe, she ſayed of her ſelfe theſe words. They shall thinke me a falſe and blind Prophetiſſe; but when they shall ſee theſe things come to paſſe, they will remember me &amp; call me no more a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiſſe, but a Prophetiſſe of the almighty God.</p>
            <p>The ſixt was called <hi>Samia,</hi> borne in the Ile of <hi>Samos,</hi> which ſaid: Hee beeing rich ſhall be borne of a poore mayde; the creatures of the earth ſhall adore him, and praiſe him for euer.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth was called <hi>Cumana,</hi> becauſe ſhee prophecied at <hi>Cumas</hi> a towne of <hi>Campania</hi> in <hi>Italie:</hi> ſhee prophecied that he ſhould come from heauen, and raigne heere in pouerty: hee ſhould rule in ſilence, and be borne of a virgen.</p>
            <p>The eight was called <hi>Heleſpontica,</hi> borne at <hi>Marmiſe</hi> in the territorie of <hi>Troy.</hi> A woman ſhall deſcend of the Iewes called <hi>Marie,</hi> and of her ſhall be borne the ſonne of God, named <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and that without carnall copulation: for ſhee ſhall be a Virgen before and after his birth: he ſhall be both God and man, he ſhall fulfill the lawes of the Iewes, and ſhall adde his owne lawe thereunto: and his kingdome ſhall remaine for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <p>The ninth was of <hi>Frigia,</hi> and prophecied in the towne of <hi>Ancire,</hi> one of her ſayings were; The Higheſt ſhall come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, and ſhall confirme the counſaile in heauen, and a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen ſhall be ſhewed in the valleis of the deſerts.</p>
            <p>The tenth was <hi>Albunea,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Tiburtina,</hi> becauſe ſhe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14164:8"/>
was borne at <hi>Tiber,</hi> 15 mile from <hi>Rome.</hi> The inuiſible Word ſhall be borne of a virgin: hee ſhall conuerſe among ſinners, and ſhall of them be deſpiſed. <hi>Lactantius Firmianus</hi> reherſeth diuerſe of their prophecies, without making any particular mention of them: they are to be referred ſpecially notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (as it ſhould ſeeme) vnto <hi>Sybilla Samberta,</hi> who wrote 24 Bookes in verſe; chiefely intreating of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, miracles, and life of <hi>Christ,</hi> whereunto, the ſayings of all the other <hi>Sibylles</hi> are conformable.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Austine</hi> likewiſe in the 23 chapter of his 18 booke <hi>De ciuitate Dei,</hi> reciteth thoſe prophecies as followeth. Then hee ſhall be taken by the wicked hands of the Infidels, and they ſhall giue him buffets on his face with theyr ſacriledge hands, and they ſhall ſpit vppon him with theyr foule and curſed mouthes. Hee ſhall turne vnto them his ſhoulders ſuffering them to be whipped; yea hee ſhall holde his peace without ſpeaking ere a word, to the end that none ſhall knowe from whence his words proceedeth. He ſhal alſo be crowned vvith thornes; they ſhall giue him gall to eate, &amp; vineger to drinke: behold the feaſt that they ſhall make him: in ſo much that thou ignorant and blind people ſhall not know thy God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing among men, but thou ſhalt crowne him with thornes, mingling for him gal and vineger. Then the vaile of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhal rend, and at midde day it ſhal be darke night for the ſpace of three houres. So the iuſt ſhal die the death, and his death or ſleepe ſhall continue three dayes: and when he ſhall haue been in the bowels of the earth, hee ſhal reſuſcit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> moreouer, lib. 4. chap. 15. reherſeth theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of them. Hee ſhal raiſe the dead, the impotent and lame ſhall goe, and runne nimbly, the deafe ſhall heare, the blind ſhal ſee, the dumbe ſhall ſpeake freely. And a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that, ſayeth, with fiue loaues and two fiſhes, he ſhal nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the Deſerts 5000 men, and the fragments thereof ſhall be ſufficient to ſatisfie many more. Many other thinges were foretold by theſe <hi>Sibyls,</hi> as well of the ruines of great States as of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14164:8"/>
            <head>The twelue Apostles with theyr martyrdome.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IAmes</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> called <hi>maior,</hi> for that hee vvas choſen to be an Apoſtle, was ſent to conuert <hi>Spayne,</hi> from whence by reaſon of the obſtinacie of the people, (for he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in all but nine perſons) hee returned ſhortly againe to preach in <hi>Iudea.</hi> Where by the enuy of a Iewiſh Biſhop called <hi>Abiathar,</hi> he was accuſed, and beheadded by the conſent of <hi>Herod Agrippa.</hi> His body was conuaied by his diſciples firſt to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Spayne,</hi> where it yet remaineth in <hi>Compostella</hi> a famous pilgrimage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iames</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Alphey,</hi> called <hi>minor,</hi> for that hee vvas laſt choſen, hee was the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and that by the ſpace of thirty yeeres: and then as he was preaching in the Temple, hee was throwne headlong downe by the Phariſes, and by them ſtoned to death. He was buried by the Temple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon</hi> by Chriſt called <hi>Peter,</hi> through the indignation of <hi>Nero,</hi> becauſe he had ouercome <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> was crucified with his head downeward, according as he deſired.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul,</hi> after his conuerſion called <hi>Paul,</hi> after hee had endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and eſcaped many dangers and torments, as beating with rods, and put in the ſtocks by <hi>Philippus;</hi> ſtoned in <hi>Listria,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to wilde beaſts in <hi>Epheſis,</hi> bound and beaten in <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and many others: laſtly came to <hi>Rome,</hi> whereby the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment of <hi>Nero,</hi> hee was beheaded (becauſe hee was a <hi>Romaine</hi> borne) the ſame day that <hi>Peter</hi> was crucified. <hi>Paule</hi> in ſteade of <hi>Iohn,</hi> becauſe hee ended not his life with martir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phillip,</hi> after hee had preached through the whole Countrie of <hi>Scythia,</hi> and conuerted a great part thereof in the ſpace of 20 yeares, was at the laſt in the Cittie of <hi>Ierapolis</hi> (when hee had there extirped the hereſie of the <hi>Hebeonits</hi>) faſtened to the croſſe, and ſo died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bartholmew</hi> went to preach in <hi>India,</hi> and afterward cam to <hi>Albania</hi> a Cittie of <hi>Armenia</hi> the greater, where he conuerted the King of that Cittie, and deſtroyed the idols, wherefore by the commaundment of <hi>Astiagus</hi> brother to the King <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemius,</hi> whom hee had conuerted, hee was flead quicke. His bodie was afterwards brought to <hi>Italie,</hi> and is as ſome ſay at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14164:9"/>
               <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Andrew, Simon Peters</hi> brother, went firſt to preach in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia,</hi> and afterward preached in <hi>Scithya:</hi> but laſtly hee was taken at <hi>Patras</hi> a Cittie of <hi>Achaia,</hi> by <hi>Egeas,</hi> Proconſull of that Prouince: who becauſe he had conuerted his wife <hi>Maximilla,</hi> caſt him in priſon, where he was ſore beaten, and laſtly ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out and bound on a ſlope croſſe, to augment his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas</hi> preached the Goſpell to the <hi>Parthians, Medes, Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Hyrcanians, Bragmans,</hi> and conuerted a great part of <hi>India.</hi> He was by the infidells throwne into a burning furnace, and came out vnhurt. Finally, becauſe he prayed God to deſtroy the idole of the ſonne, which the infidells would haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled him to worſhip, hee was by them thruſt through with ſpeares and ſwords.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathew,</hi> after he had preached much in <hi>Iudea,</hi> he went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> &amp; there conuerted the greateſt part of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Finally, hauing newly ended his prayers, and lefting vp his hands to heauen by the altar, certaine ſpies came behinde him, and ranne him through with their ſwords: which was donne by the commaundment of a King of thoſe Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudas,</hi> called alſo <hi>Thadeus,</hi> after the aſſention of our Lord, was ſent by <hi>Thomas</hi> to heale <hi>Abagar</hi> King of <hi>Ediſſa:</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he preached in <hi>Ponte,</hi> and <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and conuerted many cruell and barbarous people. Laſtly, hee came to <hi>Perſia,</hi> where for counfounding of their idols, was ſuddenly runne vppon, and murdered by the Paymin Biſhops of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. He is buried at <hi>Netre</hi> a Cittie of <hi>Armenia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon,</hi> called <hi>Chananeus,</hi> brother to <hi>Thadeus,</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> the leſſe; after he had preached in <hi>Egipt,</hi> returned to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whereof by the conſent of the Apoſtles, he was made Biſhop after the martirdome of his brother <hi>Iames.</hi> As touching his death and martirdome, ſome ſay that he ſufferred with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iudas Thadeus</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> others, that he was through the enuie of Heretikes, accuſed to bee a Chriſtian afore the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull <hi>Atticus,</hi> and therefore crucified, as his maiſter was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathy,</hi> after the aſcention of Chriſt, choſen by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to ſupply <hi>Iudas</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, was borne at <hi>Bethlem,</hi> &amp; deſcended
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14164:9"/>
of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> he preched altogether in <hi>Iudea,</hi> where laſtly he was accuſed by his enemies of periurie or rather blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, and therefore hee was condemned to be ſtoned to death by two men, during which torment, one ſmote him with a hatchet, and ſo he ſuffered martyrdome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The tenne perſecutions vnder the Romaine Emperors.</head>
            <p>THe firſt beganne in the 13 yeere of the raigne of <hi>Nero,</hi> in ſuch ſort, that the Chriſtians were faine to hide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in caues of the earth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond began in the 12 yeere of the raigne of <hi>Domici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who cauſed S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt to be put in a veſſell of burning oyle, whereof he receiued no hurt.</p>
            <p>The third began in the tenth yeere of the raigne of <hi>Traian,</hi> which ceaſed afterwards by the pitty and meanes of <hi>Plinie,</hi> 2. prefect of the Empire.</p>
            <p>The fourth beganne vnder <hi>Marcus Antoninus,</hi> and <hi>Aurelius Commodus</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>The fift began at the commaundement of the Emperour <hi>Seuerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt began by the indignation of <hi>Maximinus,</hi> who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially perſecuted the Clergie.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth began vnder the Emperour <hi>Decius,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued cruelly.</p>
            <p>The eight began vnder the Emperor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius,</hi> who though at the firſt he were a Chriſtian, yet afterwards beeing corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by certaine herericks, he became a moſt cruell perſecuter of Chriſt his Church.</p>
            <p>The ninth began vnder the Emperour <hi>Aurelianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth began by the commandement of the Emperors <hi>Diocleſianus</hi> and <hi>Maximianus Herculeus:</hi> this perſecution was farre more cruell and generall then any of the reſt: inſomuch that <hi>Diocleſianus</hi> in the orient, and <hi>Maximianus</hi> in the occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, deſtroyed all Churches, and tormented the Chriſtians with all ſtrange torments.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The eyght times that Rome hath beene taken.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ROme</hi> was firſt taken by the <hi>Gaules,</hi> vnder the conduct of theyr captaine <hi>Brennus,</hi> the yeere of the foundation of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14164:10"/>
the Cittie about 365, the yeere of the world 4835, &amp; the yere before Chriſt 364. This <hi>Brennus</hi> is by the Britain &amp; Engliſh Chronicles reported to be a <hi>Britain,</hi> and brother to <hi>Belinus</hi> king of Britain; but neither the Chronicles of <hi>Rome</hi> nor of <hi>Gaule</hi> doe ſpeake of any ſuch matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was ſecondly taken by <hi>Alaricke</hi> king of <hi>Gothes,</hi> after he had held his ſiege to it the ſpace of two yeeres, which befell the yeere of the foundation of the Citty 1164, the yere of our Lord 412, and the 25 yeere of the Empire of <hi>Honorius.</hi> It is written in the Chronicles of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that as <hi>Alaricke</hi> (beeing a Chriſtian,) marched with his hoſt towards <hi>Rome,</hi> a certaine Munck, of holy life and great authority, came vnto him, who hauing audience, admoniſhed and counſailed him to breake of that euill purpoſe, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that he was a Chriſtian, and that for Gods ſake hee would moderate his wrath, and that he ſhould not take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the ſhedding of Chriſtian blood, ſith that <hi>Rome</hi> had not in any reſpect offended him. Vnto whom <hi>Alaricke</hi> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, Thou muſt vnderſtand man of God, that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not of mine owne will that I goe againſt <hi>Rome:</hi> but contrarily I aſſure thee, that euery day there commeth vnto me a man, which conſtraineth and importuneth me thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſaying vnto me, Haſten thee, goe againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> deſtroy it vtterly, and make it deſolate. At which wordes the religious man beeing aſtoniſhed, durſt not reply: and ſo the King fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was thirdly taken by <hi>Genſericke</hi> king of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andales,</hi> the yeere of the foundation of the citty 1208. the yeere of Chriſt 456. who ſacked and burned it in many places, which befell in the Empire of <hi>Marcian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was fourthly taken by <hi>Totila</hi> King of <hi>Gothes,</hi> vvho becauſe hee could not obtaine peace of the Emperour <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> (who truſted too much in the power of his Lieutenant <hi>Belliſarius</hi>) commaunded the Cittizens to auoyde the Cittie, and afterward burned, ſacked, and deſtroyed almoſt all the Cittie, walls, and the Capitall, and made it altogether deſolate: in ſo much that neuer ſince it could be repayred according to the firſt forme, although a while after <hi>Belliſarius</hi> peopled and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14164:10"/>
repaired a great part thereof, and calling againe the old inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, fortified and ſtrengthned much the walls. This deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and of all other moſt lamentable, happened the yeare after the foundation of the Citty 1300: afther <hi>Christ</hi> 548, &amp; the 21 yeare of the Empire of <hi>Iustinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was fiftly taken by the ſame <hi>Totila,</hi> King of <hi>Goths;</hi> after that <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had repeopled &amp; repayred it: but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before he had almoſt deſtroyed it, hee now called againe the Cittizens, which were fled at his comming, and trauailed all he could to reſtore and repaire that which he had deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and behaued himſelfe towards his ſubiects, and eſpecially towards the <hi>Romaines,</hi> not like a ſtranger but a father. This happened but three yeares after he had deſtroyed it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was ſixtly taken by the <hi>Mores &amp; Sarrazins,</hi> followers of <hi>Mohomet</hi> his law, which in great multitude came into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and in the yeare of our Lord 833, ſitting in <hi>Rome, Gregorie</hi> the fourth, &amp; gouering the Empire <hi>Lewis</hi> the firſt; beſieged, tooke, and ſacked <hi>Rome,</hi> prophaning the Temple of Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> which donne they returned to their ſhippes, charged with prayes and priſoners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was ſeauenthly taken by <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of that name, Emperour of <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſitting in <hi>Rome, Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth: this time <hi>Rome</hi> was moſt cruelly deſtroyed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that both the armies of the <hi>Pope</hi> and the Emperour ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, and fought long within the Cittie, and the <hi>Capitole,</hi> which had beene before (deſtroyed) was now againe (repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) which befell the yeare of our Lord 1082: authors write that <hi>Rome</hi> neuer was ſo much endomaged at any thing, as at this, for the lamentable deſtruction that was donne by the <hi>Normans</hi> on the <hi>Popes</hi> ſide, and <hi>Germaines</hi> for the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was laſt taken by <hi>Charles,</hi> the laſt Duke of <hi>Bourbon:</hi> who being ſlaine as he ſcaled the walls at the firſt aſſaut, and by that chance, the ſouldiers being in libertie and without a head, pittifully deſtroyed the Cittie, and committed all kind of enormities, and barbarous cruelties, ſauing that they burned not the Churches, although they ſpoyled and robbed them to the vttermoſt, for a great part of the armie were <hi>Germaines,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14164:11"/>
and moſt of the <hi>Germaines Lutherans.</hi> This aduerſitie happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Rome</hi> the yeare of our Sauiour 1527, ſitting at <hi>Rome Clement</hi> the ſeauenth: and gouering the Empire <hi>Charles</hi> the fift.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſeauen Electors of the Emperour of Germanie.</head>
            <p>THree Eccleſiaſticall: that is to meane, the Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Magonce,</hi> called the <hi>Archchancelour</hi> of <hi>Germanie:</hi> the Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Colen,</hi> called the <hi>Archecancelour</hi> of <hi>Italie:</hi> and the Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Treues,</hi> called the <hi>Archechancelour</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Foure Temporall: the Marquis of <hi>Brandebourg,</hi> great Chamberlaine of the Empire: the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> beareth the ſword before the Emperour: the Earle <hi>Palatin</hi> of <hi>Rhene, Dapifer,</hi> of carrying the plate: the King of <hi>Baeme,</hi> Taſter to the Emperour, or Karuer. Theſe Electors were firſt ordained by the Emperour <hi>Othon</hi> third of that name, in the yeare of our Lord 1000, to take away the diſſention which before times had beene for the chooſing of Emperours: and ordained moreouer, that being choſen by theſe ſeauen Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, he ſhould be called <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but being afterwards crowned by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> he ſhould be called <hi>Augustus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The three crownes of the Emperour.</head>
            <p>THe firſt Crowne is of ſiluer, for the Realme of <hi>Germaine,</hi> and is kept at <hi>Aix</hi> the Chappell. The ſecond Crowne is of yron, for the Realme of <hi>Lombardie,</hi> and is kept at <hi>Modene,</hi> a little Towne not farre from <hi>Milan.</hi> And the third of gold, for the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> where it is kept.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The xij. Peers, or Pairs of Fraunce.</head>
            <p>IN the Realme of <hi>France</hi> to be a Peer, is the greateſt digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnder the King, for that in many thinges they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt equall authority with the King; for Peer in the French tongue ſignifieth equall. But becauſe it might be too prolixe a matter to ſpeak of theyr prerogatiues, it ſhall ſuffice to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, and each of theyr offices at the ſacring or coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a new King. Theſe ancient Peers are twelue in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; whereof ſixe are of the Clergy, and ſixe are Lay men:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14164:11"/>
the ſixe of the Clergie with theyr offices at the corronation, are the Archbiſhop and Duke of <hi>Reins,</hi> which hath his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed charge to oynt and conſecrate the King, the Biſhop and Duke of <hi>Laon,</hi> who office is to bring the holy Ampoule, or diuine water, wherwith the King is annointed: the Biſhop and Duke of <hi>Langres,</hi> whoſe office is to bring the ſcepter &amp; the hand of iuſtice; the Biſhop and Earle of <hi>Beauuais,</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Kings cloake; the Biſhop &amp; Earle of <hi>Chaalons,</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Kings Ring; the Biſhop and Earle of <hi>Noyon,</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Kings gyrdle. The ſixe temporall Peers with theyr offices at the corronation, are the Duke of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> Deane or chiefe of the reſt, whoſe office is to bring the kings crowne: the Duke of <hi>Guyen</hi> bringeth the firſt ſquare banner: the duke of <hi>Normandie</hi> bringeth the ſecond ſquare banner: the Earle of Earle of <hi>Tolowze</hi> bringeth the Kings ſpurres: the Earle of <hi>Champaine</hi> bringeth the kingly banner, or the ſtandart of warre: and the Earle of <hi>Flaunders</hi> bringeth the Kings ſword. And although the fiue firſt temporall Peerdoms be vnited to the crowne, and the ſixt bee ſubiect to another Prince, yet at at the Kings corronation, there are other noble men appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſupply theyr roome and offices. Theſe be the twelue ancient Peers, although ſince theyr creation others haue been made, which though they haue like authoritie to iudge in the Court of Parliament, yet they want offices at the Kings coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and beare not that maieſtie that the other Pees doe, for that they are not of ſo great antiquitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The eyght Parliaments of Fraunce.</head>
            <p>THE chiefe &amp; generalleſt iuſtice of the realme of <hi>France,</hi> is continually kept in eyght Citties, wherein are Pallaces made expreſly for that purpoſe: and this generall kind of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is deuided into eyght parts, according to the eyght Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and euery of them are called Parliaments, which differ very little from our Termes: but whereas theſe are but foure times in a yeere, thoſe are continually kept, each of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in ſtead of our Lord Chancelor, a chiefe Preſident.</p>
            <p>The firſt and chiefeſt of theſe Parliaments is that of <hi>Paris,</hi> called the Court of the Peers of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> and to the equitie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14164:12"/>
and iudgement of this Parliament, many forraine Kings and Princes haue ſubmitted themſelues in matters of greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, as to the moſt venerable and chiefeſt Senate of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in the world. Such were the Emperor <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, called <hi>Barberouſſe,</hi> king of both <hi>Sicils,</hi> when he ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe to the iudgement of this Court of Parliament, as touching all the controuerſies of his Empire and kingdoms, which he had againſt Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth: <hi>Philip</hi> prince of <hi>Tarente,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> who ſumbitted them ſelues to this Parliament, for the controuerſie betwixt them vpon the expences of the recouery of the Empire of <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> ſubiect to the Empire, and the Lord <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Chastillon,</hi> who ſubmitted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lues to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Court, as concerning the limitation of their lands and poſſeſsions: the Daulphin of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienne,</hi> &amp; the Earle of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy</hi> ſummitted themſelues to the iudgement of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, concerning the ſute betwixt them, for the homage of the Marquiſat of <hi>Saluces.</hi> Moreouer, without the conſent of this Parliament, it hath not beene ſeene that the Kings of <hi>Fraunce</hi> haue done or paſſed any matter of importance tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſtate of the Realme, ſo much is it reſpected both within the Realme and abroad. This Court of Parliament was firſt ordeyned by <hi>Phillip the fayre,</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Parliament is at <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> for the countries of <hi>Gwyen, Gaſcoine, Zaintonge, Perigort,</hi> part of <hi>Poictou,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and was firſt ordained by <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeauenth.</p>
            <p>The third Parliament is at <hi>Rouën,</hi> for the Dukedome of <hi>Normandie,</hi> firſt made Exchequer by <hi>Phillip the fayre,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards continuall Parliament by <hi>Lewes</hi> the twelfth.</p>
            <p>The fourth Parliament is at <hi>Toulowze,</hi> firſt ordained for certaine times of the yeere by <hi>Phillip the fayre,</hi> and afterwards made continuall by <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeauenth, for the Country of <hi>Languedoc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift Parliament is at <hi>Grenoble,</hi> for the country of <hi>Daul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Lewes</hi> the xj.</p>
            <p>The ſixt Parliament is at <hi>Dijon</hi> for the Dukedome of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie,</hi> it was likewiſe ordained by the ſayd <hi>Lewes</hi> the xj.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth Parliament is at <hi>Aix,</hi> for the Earledome of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14164:12"/>
               <hi>Proueme,</hi> appointed by <hi>Lewes</hi> the xij.</p>
            <p>The eyght Parliament is at <hi>Renes</hi> in <hi>Britaine,</hi> ordained by <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond. Of all theſe Parliaments <hi>Paris</hi> Parliament is the chiefe; and certaine caſes are reſerued to be iudged only at the Parliament of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſeauen Saxon Kingdomes that England was once deuided into.</head>
            <p>THe firſt, was the Kingdome of <hi>Kent:</hi> which had his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Saxon Hengist,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 476: and the fift yeare of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ortiger</hi> King of <hi>Britaine</hi> his laſt raigne (for he had beene depoſed) the Kingdome continued 342 yeares, till that <hi>Egbert</hi> King of <hi>Westſaxons</hi> vanquiſhed <hi>Baldred</hi> laſt King thereof, and ioyned it to his owne King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Kingdome was of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> or <hi>Southſaxons,</hi> which began by the <hi>Saxon Ella,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 482: and the ſecond yeare of <hi>Aurelambroſe</hi> King of <hi>Britaine.</hi> This kingdome continued not aboue 112 yeares.</p>
            <p>The third kingdome was of <hi>Estangles,</hi> or eaſt <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and contained <hi>Northfolke</hi> and <hi>Southfolke:</hi> it was firſt begunne by the <hi>Saxon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ffa,</hi> about the yeare of our Lord 492: and the 11 yeare of <hi>Aurell Ambroſe</hi> king of <hi>Britaine.</hi> This kingdome continued 376 yeares; the laſt king whereof was Saint <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> martired by the <hi>Danes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth was the kingdome of <hi>Westſaxons,</hi> containing the Weſt countrie of England, and had his beginning by the <hi>Saxon Cerdicus,</hi> the yeare of our Lord 522: and the fift yeare of <hi>Arthur</hi> the great king of <hi>Britaine,</hi> and endured from the firſt yeare of <hi>Cerdicus</hi> to the laſt of <hi>Alured,</hi> the tearme of 378 yeares. The kings of this Countrie ſubdued at length all the other ſixe kingdomes, which <hi>Egbert</hi> beganne, and <hi>Alured</hi> finiſhed, making of all the South part of this Iland one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie.</p>
            <p>The fift was the kingdome of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> containing the Countries betwixt the Riuer of <hi>Humber</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> had his beginning of the <hi>Saxon Ida,</hi> king of <hi>Brenicia;</hi> the yeare of our Lord 547: and the ſecond or laſt yeare of the raigne of <hi>Aurele Canon,</hi> king of <hi>Britaine.</hi> This kingdome of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14164:13"/>
was at the firſt deuided into two kingdomes, the one was called the <hi>Brenicia,</hi> which bended towards the North, &amp; the other <hi>Deyra</hi> (about) the Countrie of <hi>Durham:</hi> and this kingdome continued ſome while vnder one king, ſometime vnder two, the tearme of 409 yeares: firſt vnder the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and then vnder the <hi>Danes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt kingdome was of the Eaſt <hi>Saxons,</hi> or <hi>Eſſex,</hi> which beganne by the <hi>Saxon Sobert,</hi> the yeare of our Lord about 614: &amp; continued from the beginning of the raigne of <hi>Sebert</hi> till the eight yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the elder, 293 yeares.</p>
            <p>The 7. kingdome was of <hi>Mercia,</hi> containing <hi>Huntington<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, Hertfortſhire, Glocesterſhire,</hi> and others: and was the greateſt of all the other, taking his beginning of the <hi>Saxon Penda,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 626: after the comming of <hi>Hengist</hi> 126 yeares: during the raigne of <hi>Cadwan</hi> king of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and continued from <hi>Penda</hi> till that <hi>Edward</hi> the elder cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out the <hi>Danes,</hi> about 280 yeeres. Theſe 7. kingdoms of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> beſide that of <hi>Walles</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> were all contained at once in this Iland of <hi>Britaine,</hi> and continued along ſpace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Fiue Orders of Chiualrie, which continue at this day among Princes.</head>
            <p>THe firſt and ancienteſt of theſe Orders of Chiualrie, or Knighthood, is the Order of the Garter, inſtituted the yere of our Lord 1348 in <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> chiefe Citty of the duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Guyne</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> by <hi>Edward</hi> the third, king of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and then poſſeſſor of that Dukedome: which order hee conſecrated, and dedicated to S. <hi>George,</hi> though the motiue of the inſtitution thereof, proceeded of the loſſe of a Garter, which he ſuppoſed to haue been the Counteſſe of <hi>Salsburies,</hi> but I referre the Reader to the Chronicle. And it hapned in this manner: as one day he was entertaining her with pleaſant talke, a Garter chanced to vnloſe and fall downe, the King endeuouring to take it vp, wittingly cauſed ſuch a ieſt as moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Noble-men to laughter: the Counteſſe thereat blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and blaming that more then ſeemely familiaritie of the King, for that he had cauſed ſuch a ieſt among the aſsiſtance,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14164:13"/>
ſaid ſharply to him, and the reſt, <hi>Honi ſoit qui mal y penſe:</hi> which engliſhed, is, <hi>diffamed be hee which euill therein thinketh.</hi> And the King in recompence of his raſhnes, ſaid forth-with, that before it were long, thoſe Noble men which had made a ieſt and laughing at the Garter fallen downe, ſhould eſteeme themſelues much honored to weare it for a marke of honour and chiualrie, and thereupon ordayned the ſaide Order, and dedicated it to S. <hi>George,</hi> and made thereof 26 Knights, and ordained that they ſhould weare their clokes of violet cullour Veluet; their hoods of redde Veluet, lined with white Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske, theyr baſes of redde Veluet, and vnder the left knee a blew Garter, buckled with golde, garniſhed with precious ſtones, and about it wrought the wordes of the Counteſſe of <hi>Salisbury, HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE,</hi> and a coller of gold full of red &amp; white Roſes, with an Image of S. <hi>George</hi> hanging thereon: &amp; about theſe Roſes are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thoſe words which are in the Garter. This Order is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated on S. <hi>George</hi> his day, beeing the 23 of Aprill.</p>
            <p>And although it was firſt ordained at <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> yet the ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, would that the ſiedge and place of the ſolemniſing thereof ſhould be at the Church of <hi>Winſor,</hi> heere in <hi>England,</hi> where at the ſame time he founded Chanons or a Chanonry, for the better proſperitie of the Knights of his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>The ſecond order in antiquitie, is the order of the Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, inſtituted anno dom. 1356 by <hi>Amé</hi> the ſixt of that name, Earle of <hi>Sauoye,</hi> and ſurnamed the greene Knight. The Knights of this order weare a great collor of gold, made wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with three laces which are called of loue, wherein are enterlaced theſe words, <hi>FERT, FERT, FERT,</hi> euerie letter importing his Latin word, thus, <hi>F. fortitudo, E. eius, R. Rhodum, T. tenuit:</hi> that is, his force hath conquered <hi>Rhodes:</hi> and at this Collor hangeth an image of our Lady, and of an Angell ſaluting her, and for that occaſion is called the Order of the Annuntiation. This Earle ordained this Order in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>Amé</hi> the great, Earle of <hi>Sauoye,</hi> which ſuccoured the Knights of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> when they conquered the Ile of <hi>Rhodes</hi> vpon the <hi>Turkes,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1310.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14164:14"/>The third in antiquitie is the Order of the golden Fleece founded vpon the fable of the golden Fleece, that <hi>Iaſon</hi> with the other <hi>Argonautes</hi> went to ſeeke in the Ile of <hi>Colohos,</hi> which is to meane, that hee went to the mine of gold: and ordained by <hi>Phillip</hi> the ſecond, ſurnamed the good Duke of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1430: the complete number of which Order are 24 Knights: and weare their cloakes and hoods of Scarlat, garded with imbroderie, made with flames of fire, and a Collor of gold, made with fire ſtones ſparkling out fire, whereat hangeth a Fleece of gold: and appointed for the celebrating of that Order Saint <hi>Andrewes</hi> day, being the 30 of Nouember. But the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift (heyre of the houſe of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> and chiefe of that Order) changed their apparell, and ordained that their clokes ſhould bee of crimſon Veluet, and their hoodes of violet coullor Veluet, and that vnderneath they ſhould were a Caſſoke of cloath of ſiluer.</p>
            <p>The fourth in antiquitie is the Order of Saint <hi>Michaell</hi> the Archangell, inſtituted by <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11, King of <hi>France,</hi> the firſt day of Auguſt, in the yeare of our Lord 1469: and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that of that Order there ſhould be 36 Knights, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of name and of armes without reprooch, of whom hee himſelfe was chiefe and Soueraigne, and after him his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors Kings of <hi>Fraunce.</hi> And the brothers or companions of this order were bound, at the receiuing thereof, to forſake and leaue all other Orders, if any they had, either of a Prince or any companie, onely excepting Emperours, Kings, and Dukes, which beſide this Order, might weare that Order whereof they weare chiefe, with the agreement and conſent of the King and confrarie of the ſayd Order: and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the ſayd Kings of <hi>Fraunce</hi> might weare beſide his owne, the Order of other Emperours, Kings, and Dukes. And for the connoiſſance of this Order, and the Knights thereof, hee gaue to euery of them a Coller of gold, wrought with Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell ſhells, enterlacing on another with a double pointing Ribon of ſilke, with golden Tagges, which King <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, becauſe his name was <hi>Francis,</hi> changed into a white Friers or <hi>Franciſcans</hi> girdle, made of a twiſted corde: and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14164:14"/>
hangeth on that Collor a tablet of Saint <hi>Michaell</hi> vppon a Rocke: of the inſtitution of this Order is made a booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining 98 Articles, wherein are ſet downe the things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the Knights of this Order are ſubiect.</p>
            <p>The fift Order is that of the holy Ghoſt, inſtituted by <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the third, King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> at this preſent, on New yeares day in the yeare of our Lord 1579: of this alſo is written a booke, containing the Articles whereunto the Knights there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are bound. Among the which I haue principally noted one, that is, to defend and ſuſtaine the Clergie: for the king doth giue to euery of them the rent of certaine Abbeys, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houſes, or other ſpiritually Lands, whereof they ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a certaine ſtipend, to the entertaining of a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of religious perſons, in euery religious houſe vnder him; and for that benefite, are ſworne at their entring into the ſayd Order, alwaies to defend the ſpiritualitie, and maintaine the Clergie in their priuiledges: but how they keepe their oath, it is well ſeene in euery place of their ſpirituall poſſeſſions: and thereof my ſelfe haue often times had oculare experience, for trauelling in that Countrie, and paſſing often times by good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religious houſes, I haue ſometimes for recreation (hauing wel tried the curtious demeanor, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly religious men vſe towards ſtrangers that come to view their houſes) entred into ſundry of them: where I haue diuers times beene ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently enformed by the religious, how the king had giuen the rents and poſſeſſions of their houſes to the Knights of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with the conditions already rehearſed, which Knights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them ſuch bare exhibitation, that by reaſon it is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to entertaine the fourth part of the number by them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, almoſt all of them are conſtrained either to forſake their houſes, &amp; begge, or elſe there to ſtarue: through which occaſion, many goodly religious houſes are of late fallen in decay for want of reparation, trimming vp, and inhabiting, and will doe more and more without a redreſſe. And this haue I learned in diuers religious houſes, beſide the common murmering of the Clergie: and ſo wee may ſee, how theſe Knights, called, of the holy ſpirit, for to defend and maintaine the ſpiritualitie, doe vnder pretence thereof, rob, and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14164:15"/>
waſt the ſpirituall poſſeſſions: ſo that it may ſeeme only to be a pollicie (vnder the correction of better iudgement) put in the kings head, to diminiſh ſpirituall liuings (which in that Country are wonderfull great) &amp; ſatisfie his prodigall minde, in rewarding by that meanes his flatterers; becauſe through his exceeding lauiſhneſſe, hee is ſcarce able otherwiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them. The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> conſidering what diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of Church-lands, and decay of Gods ſeruice, commeth through this Order, in the Realme of <hi>Fraunce;</hi> will not grant the confirmation thereof, although the King hath beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant for the ſame: but notwithſtanding the Popes miſliking thereof, the Order is maintained, though to the great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the religion in that Country. Yea at the laſt celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, which was on New-yeeres day eeuen, 1581, I ſaw three Biſhops were admitted into that Order, the conniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance wherof is a Doue, repreſenting the holy Ghoſt, wraught in Orenge tauny Veluet, garniſhed about with ſiluer beames, which the Knights of that Order weare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vpon their clokes, before their hart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The <hi>13</hi> Cantons of Swiſſerland.</head>
            <p>THE inhabitants of <hi>Heluetia</hi> or <hi>Swiſſerland,</hi> after they had emancipated themſelues from the yoke of the Empire, and expelled the nobilitie of the Emperiall faction, began to make leagues and confederacies one towne with another, to fortifie themſelues by that meanes againſt forraine inuaſions, if any hapned. And in proceſſe of time, within little more then an hundred yeeres, are increaſed to the number of 13, which they call Cantons, by which the whole Country of <hi>Swiſſe</hi> is gouerned and defended. And heere (according to theyr an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie) I place them the firſt that confederated together, and gaue example to the reſt, were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri, Swits. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderuard,</hi> Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: and theſe three by little and little, haue drawne to theyr faction all the reſt that followeth, <hi>Lucerne, Zurich,</hi> Citties: <hi>Glaris, Zug,</hi> Villages: <hi>Berne, Fribourg, Soullcurre, Baſle, Schaffouſe,</hi> Citties: <hi>Appenſel,</hi> village. Whereof 7. profeſſe the Romiſh religion, j. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri, Swits, Vnderuard, Zug, Lucerne, Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14164:15"/>
and <hi>Soullcurre,</hi> the reſt are <hi>Zuinglians:</hi> which diuerſitie of religion hath cauſed diſſention, and mortall warres of late yeeres among them, although they be all ſworne together to defend theyr liberties againſt ſtrangers.</p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>FINIS.</hi> Non munus ſed animus.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
